<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Osx on Tony Lawrence</title>
    <link>http://tonylawrence.com/categories/osx/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Osx on Tony Lawrence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tonyklawrence&#34;&gt;Tony Lawrence&lt;/a&gt; 2017 - Waffly Bollocks</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://tonylawrence.com/categories/osx/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing Homebrew on OSX Mavericks</title>
      <link>http://tonylawrence.com/post/unix/installing-homebrew/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tonylawrence.com/post/unix/installing-homebrew/</guid>
      <description>I choose to install all my applications via Homebrew. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to install, easy to update, works well for me and has all the required packages including everything required for Haskell. Installing Homebrew is as easy as running the following command in terminal[^brew]:
$ ruby -e &amp;quot;$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/master/install)&amp;quot;  You will be required to enter your administrator password and might be asked to install Apples Xcode developer tools and also Git versioning tool.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing corrupted time machine backups</title>
      <link>http://tonylawrence.com/post/unix/fixing-corrupted-time-machine-backups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tonylawrence.com/post/unix/fixing-corrupted-time-machine-backups/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday my MacBook Air decided that it no longer trusted my Time Machine backup and wanted to create a new one. Apart from the time this would take (20gb over WiFi) and the fact that I&amp;rsquo;d lose my current history I was a little bit wary so declined. Unfortunately this was not a the last I heard of it. Time Machine refused to back up until I started a new back up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publishing from the iCloud</title>
      <link>http://tonylawrence.com/post/blog/publishing-from-the-icloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tonylawrence.com/post/blog/publishing-from-the-icloud/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been using IA Writer as my markdown editor. I love the fact that I can use any of my iDevices and that it&amp;rsquo;s all synced in the iCloud. But how do I access the iCloud data so that I can include it in my Octopress git repository?
Show me the data On Mountain Lion (and Lion I believe) all the iCloud data is hidden away in your home directory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up Octopress</title>
      <link>http://tonylawrence.com/post/blog/setting-up-octopress-on-osx/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tonylawrence.com/post/blog/setting-up-octopress-on-osx/</guid>
      <description>When upgrading to Mountain Lion I decided to replace my existing Wordpress site with a static one. There were many reasons for this. With Wordpress I was unable to easily version control my posts into GitHub. I also had no control over and backup strategies. One of my colleagues - Toby Weston - was running Octopress so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d take a look.
Octopress is based upon Jekyll, developed and used by GitHub.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>